Leeder, Elaine Collection of Rose Pesotta Papers 5928
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Elaine Leeder Collection of Rose Pesotta Papers
1912-1961
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Pesotta, Rose
Leeder, Elaine
5928
2 cubic feet
2 linear ft.
Papers, correspondence,photographs, videotapes, motion pictures (visual works).
Correspondence, publications, photographs, and videotapes of Rose Pesotta, organizer for the International Ladies Garment Workers Union.
5704502
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, November 18, 2005
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, August 03, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Born Rakhel Peisoty in Derazhnia, Ukraine in 1896 to grain merchants, Pesotta was well educated and influenced by the Narodnaya Volya (People's Will), and eventually adopted anarchist views.
Pesotta emigrated to New York City at the age of 17 (1913), and found employment in a shirtwaist factory, she joined the ILGWU very soon after. The ILGWU was a union that represented mostly Jewish and Latina female garment workers. She was elected to the all male executive board of ILGWU Local 25 in 1920. Pesotta went to Brookwood Labor College for two years in the 1920s.
In 1933 the union sent her to Los Angeles to organize the garment workers there. The organizing of the Mexican immigrant garment workers lead to the Los Angeles Garment workers Strike of 1933. As a result of this success, she was made vice-president of the union in 1934.
In 1944, she resigned from the executive board of the union in protest of the fact that, despite 85% of the union's memebership were women, she was the sole female executive member.
Rose Pesotta died in 1965.
1896 Born in Derazhnya, Russia, November 20
1909-12 Attended Rosalia Davidoffs private girls' School
1913 Arrived in USA with her grandmother
1914 Joined Local 25, ILGWU
1914-24 Worked as a seamstress
1919 Theodore Kushnarev deported to Russia
Father dies in Derazhnya
1922 Attended Bryn Mawr summer school
Researched Sacco Vanzetti case for Local 25
1924-26 Attended Brookwood Labor College
1926-33 Worked as a seamstress in NYC
1930 Attended Wisconsin summer school
1933 Organized in Los Angeles for ILGWU
1934 Elected Vice-President of ILGWU
Sent to Puerto Rico to organize seamstresses
1935 Organized in Seattle
Organized in Buffalo
1936 Organized rubber workers in Akron
Began involvement with Powers Hapgood
Organized in Montreal
1937 Organized auto workers in Flint for CIO
Returned to Montreal to organize
Reelected to second term as vice president
Slashed by razor during Cleveland Knitting Mill Strike
1942 Vacation in Mexico
1944 Resigned as ILGWU vice president
Published "Bread Upon the Waters"
1945 Worked for Anti-Defamation League of the B'nai B'rith
1946 Traveled to Norway, Sweden, Poland
Resigned from ADL and returned to New York City as a seamstress
1949 Worked as Midwest regional director for the American Trade Union Council of the Histadrut
Death of Powers Hapgood
1950 Visited Europe and Israel
1955 Married Albert Martin (Frank Lopez)
1958 Published "Days of Our Lives"
1965 Died in Miami, Florida on December 6
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Arrangement
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Poland-Norway-Sweden
Series III. Publications and Manuscripts
Sub-Series A. Drafts of manuscripts Sub-Series B. Pamphlets and Articles Sub-Series C. Broadsides, Leaflets, Announcements Sub-Series D. Newspaper clippings
Series IV. Address File
Series V. Miscellaneous
Labor disputes -- United States; Labor unions -- United States; Labor movement -- United States.; Working class -- United States; Pesotta, Rose, 1896-; Leeder, Elaine J.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union; B'nai B'rith. Anti-defamation League
5704502
- Series I. Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged in alphabetical order.
  - American Labor Education Service, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Form letter from treasurer asking for support.
  - Bercovici, Henri, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Personal correspondence to "Albert and Rose."
  - Cypress, S., 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    1 letter-untranslated.
  - DeLeon, Solon, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Holiday greetings.
  - Farber, Litt., 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Personal.
  - Fields, Sally, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Personal correspondence on Joint Board; Millinery Workers letterhead
  - Hapwood, Powers, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Personal and business correspondence. Dicsusses John L. Lewis broadcast, the CIO, FDR, Ford Strike (1941), organizing prudential agents, Carlo Tresca murder, UAW membership, work on family farm and many other topics. Closes one letter (1940) "my Rose of Akron and Flint." Also includes four page tribute by Rose Pesotta after his death in 1949 and newspaper clippings
  - Hapwood, Powers, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hapwood, Powers, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hapwood, Powers, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Hapwood, Powers, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union, 1935-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Includes greeting card and miscellaneous
  - Jewish Labor Committee, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Miscellaneous
  - Kroportkin, S., 1951 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Personal
  - Kushnarev, Theodore, 1912-1925 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Personal love letters to Rose after his deportment to Russia
  - Kushnarev, Theodore, 1912-1926 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Kushnarev, Theodore, 1912-1927 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kushnarev, Theodore, 1912-1928 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 1946-1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Panken, Jacob, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Randolph, A. Philip (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Ticket - "Salute to A.P. Randolph," n.d.
  - Rubin, Milton, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Memo from Pesotta with biographical information
  - Saks, Hesh, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Siegel, Sophie, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Spivak, Joseph, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Thomas, Norman, 1954-1957 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Note of thanks for her financial support; letter from Thomas requesting additional biographical information in order to write an introduction for her book (1957).
  - Wohl, Paul, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Greeting card
  - Wolk, Morton, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series II. Poland-Norway-Sweden
  Rose Pesotta traveled to Poland, Norway and Sweden in 1946. She was invited by the Norwegian Labour Party to addres an International Labor Institute on the labor and social situation in the U.S. She visited Poland to see the effects of World War II. This series includes correspondence, manuscripts, notes and related pamphlets.
  - Correspondence, 1946-1948 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Notes (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes index cards with notes and addresses
  - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Includes outline of chapter heads for book (Box 1, Folder 33)
    3 pages Anti-Semitism in Russia; 3 pages Prologue; 1 page David and his family
  - Untitled manuscript which describes her trips abroad (Box 1, Folder 34)
    75 pages
  - Manuscript describing effects of the war in Norway, Sweden, and Poland. (Box 1, Folder 35)
    13 pages
  - "Flying to Poland" (4 pages); "Stockholm, Sweden" (5 pages); "Norwegian Labor Movement." (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Journals describing her trips to Warsaw, children's camps, Majdanek Death Camp, and Lodz (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Notes on Poland, Sweden and Norway (Box 1, Folder 38)
    5 pages description of her travels; 10 pages describing her visit to Norway and other manuscript drafts
  - Draft essay by Pesotta entitled "Nacht on Nebel" (Night and Fog) (Box 1, Folder 39)
    22 pages
- Series III. Publications and Manuscripts
  - Sub-Series A. Drafts of manuscripts
    Rose Pesotta's writings
    - Includes drafts and notes for chapters about Russia and Lenin (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Index cards containing research notes for her various writing projects (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Sub-Series B. Pamphlets and Articles
    Publications by others. Arranged alphabetically
    - A-D (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Beals, Carlton, "Rifle, Rule in Cuba"; Cox, James, "Hitler's Hatchet Man!" Dressmakers' Voice, December 1934; and others
    - F-K (Box 1, Folder 43)
      ILGWU, "The Communist Plague in Our Unions"
    - L-P (Box 1, Folder 44)
      Nash, Al, "The Shop Steward System"
    - Q-Z (Box 1, Folder 45)
      Articles by Walter Reuther; article by Sidney Solomon
  - Sub-Series C. Broadsides, Leaflets, Announcements
    - National Negro Conference; New York State Young Communist League; International Labor Defense and others (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Communist Party; Cloakmakers No. 70; and others (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Communist Party; Young Communist League; ILGWU Joint Board Cloak, Skirt, Dressmakers; Local 22 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Needle Trades Workers Industrial Union (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - ILGWU Locals 48-89; ILGWU General Strike Committee; Joint Board Cloak and Dressmakers; American Labor Party; Communist Party; Furriers Progressive League; Unemployed Citizens League; National Committee of the Left Whing Groups of the ILGWU: and others (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Sub-Series D. Newspaper clippings
    - Clippings, 1927-1961 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Series IV. Address File
  Includes index and business cards with addresses
  - Address file (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Address file (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Address file (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Address file (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Address file (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Address file (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Address file (Box 1, Folder 58)
- Series V. Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 59)
    Includes Pesotta's insurance cards, membership cards, identification and business cards
  - Scrapbook (Box 7)